Rachit Nigam

I am a fifth-year PhD student at Cornell University studying programming languages and computer architectures with a focus on building new toolchains to automatically generate efficient hardware accelerators. My research has produced several open-source tools that have been adopted by researchers and engineers.

Education _

Cornell University

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

2018 - Present

• Committee: Adrian Sampson (chair), Zhiru Zhang, Nate Foster, Chris De Sa

Cornell University

MASTERS IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

2018 - 2021

- Thesis: Language-Level Modeling for Hardware Constraints
- Committee: Adrian Sampson (chair), Zhiru Zhang, Nate Foster, Chris De Sa

University of Massachusetts Amherst

BACHELORS IN COMPUTER SCIENCE | SUMMA CUM LAUDE

2015 - 2018

- Thesis: Execution Control for JavaScript, Distinction with Highest Honors
- Committee: Arjun Guha (chair), Emery Berger

Refereed Publications _

ASPLOS 2023 Stepwise Debugging for Hardware Accelerators

Griffin Berlstein, Rachit Nigam, Chris Gyurgyik, Adrian Sampson

In Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems.

A Compiler Infrastructure for Accelerator Generators ASPLOS 2021

Rachit Nigam[†], Samuel Thomas[†], Zhijing Li, Adrian Sampson

 $(^{\dagger}Equally\ contributing\ authors)$

In Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems.

- Calyx has integrated in the LLVM CIRCT project and is being used to design a next-generation high-level synthesis toolchain.
- Calyx has been used as a part of four research projects and an industrial toolchain to compile PyTorch programs to customized hardware accelerators

Vectorization for Digital Signal Processors via Equality Saturation ASPLOS 2021

Alexa VanHattum, Rachit Nigam, Vincent Lee, James Bornholt, Adrian Sampson In Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems.

PLDI 2020 Predictable Accelerator Design with Time-Sensitive Affine Types

Rachit Nigam, Sachille Atapattu, Samuel Thomas, Theodore Bauer, Apurva Koti, Zhijing Li, Yuwei Ye, Adrian Sampson, Zhiru Zhang

In ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation.

Putting in All the Stops: Execution Control for JavaScript **PLDI 2018**

Samuel Baxter, Rachit Nigam, Arjun Guha, Joe Gibbs Politz, Shriram Krishnamurthi In ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation.

- The next-generation compiler for the Pyret programming language uses Stopify to provide interactive programming features.
- Stopify is the underlying technology for the Ocelot IDE and is used by hundreds of students.

Other Publications _

WOSET 2021 A Toolkit for Designing Hardware DSLs

Griffin Berlstein, Rachit Nigam, Chris Gyurgyik, Adrian Sampson

In Workshop on Open-Source EDA Technology.

LCTES 2020 A Synthesis-aided Compiler for DSP Architectures (WiP Paper)

Alexa VanHattum[†], Rachit Nigam[†], Vincent Lee, James Bornholt, Adrian Sampson

 $(^{\dagger}Equally\ contributing\ authors)$

In International Conference on Languages, Compilers, and Tools for Embedded

Systems.

SNAPL 2017 Fission: Secure Dynamic Code-Splitting for JavaScript

Arjun Guha, Jean-Baptiste Jeannin, Rachit Nigam, Jane Tangen, Rian Shambaugh

In Summit oN Advances in Programming Languages.

Experience _

Cornell University

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT

08/2018 - Present

Designing new tools and techniques for compiling high-level languages to hardware designs.

Facebook Reality Labs

RESEARCH INTERN 05/2019 - 08/2019

Applied program synthesis techniques to automatically generate correct and efficient hardware for emerging mathematical domains such as log arithmetic.

Google

SOFTWARE ENGINEERING INTERN

05/2018 - 08/2018

Implemented support for Progressive Web Applications for internal web application framework.

University of Massachusetts Amherst

Research Assistant 05/2016 - 05/2018

Developed Fission, a compiler for partitioning single-tier JavaScript program while enforcing infromation flow control.

Brown PLT, Brown University

Visiting Researcher 05/2017 - 08/2017

Developed Stopify, a source to source compiler for JavaScript that provides common debugging abstractions like stopping, stepping and break-pointing, in a browser based IDE for languages that compile to JavaScript.

${f Awards}$. Departmental Nominee, Google Fellowship 2020 Finalist, Qualcomm Innovation Fellowship 2020 Outstanding Teaching Assistant, Cornell CIS 2019 Dean's Merit Scholarship, UMass Amherst 2018 Honors Research Fellowship, UMass Amherst 2017 Racket Summer School Scholarship, University of Utah 2017 CMMRS Travel Scholarship, Max Planck Institute 2017 Finalist, Best Project in Public Interest, HackUMass IV 2016 ICFP Travel Scholarship, ICFP 16 2016 Chancellor's Scholarship, UMass Amherst 2015 Presentations _ MathWorks Code Generation Forum, Invited Talk 2022 AMD, Invited Talk 2022 Google, Invited Talk 2022 Brown University, Invited Talk 2022 Northeastern University, Invited Talk 2022 Wellesley College, Guest Lecture 2021 University of Washington, A Compiler Infrastructure for Accelerator Generators 2021 ASPLOS, A Compiler Infrastructure for Accelerator Generators 2021 LLVM CIRCT Group, A Compiler Infrastructure for Accelerator Generators 2021 PLDI, Predictable Accelerator Design with Time-Sensitive Affine Types 2020 University of California, Berkeley, Predictable Accelerator Design 2020 University of Washington, Predictable Accelerator Design 2020 Imperial College London, Predictable Accelerator Design 2020 2019 **Princeton University**, Predictable Accelerator Design **NEPLS**, Web-based Debugging for Free 2017 Academic Service _ External Review & Artifact Evaluation Committees, OOPSLA 23 2023 Social Chair, PLDI 23 2022 Organizer, 2nd Workshop on Languages, Tools, and Techniques for Accelerator Design 2021 Social Chair, PLDI 22 2021 Organizer, 1st Workshop on Languages, Tools, and Techniques for Accelerator Design 2021 Social Chair, PLDI 21 2021 Sub-reviewer, ISCA 21 2021 Artifact Evaluation Committee, OOPSLA 20 2020 Artifact Evaluation Committee, PLDI 20 2020 Artifact Evaluation Committee, PLDI 19 2019 Volunteer, SPLASH 18 2018

Vice-President of CS Graduate Organization, Cornell CIS	2020
Organizer, CAPRA External Talk Series	2020
Organizer, Programming Languages Retreat	2019
Member of Graduate Admissions Committee, Cornel CIS	2019
Mentor, Expand Your Horizons, Cornell	2019
Mentor, Eureka! Girls Inc.	2016